Finding Aid for Howard M. Ehrmann papers, 1927-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Howard M. Ehrmann papers 1927-1968
Ehrmann, Howard Meredith, 1898-
851197 Aa 2
Historian, chairman of the Department of History at University of Michigan. The series in the collection include Biographical/Personal; Course Materials; Correspondence (general and University of Michigan); Research and Grant files; and Articles and Reviews.
1.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Howard Ehrmann (donor no. 2721 ). The bulk of the collection came from his wife Emma Ehrmann in 1993.
The collection is open to research.
Howard Meredith Ehrmann was born in Terre Haute, Indiana on February 16, 1898. He attended DePauw University from 1916 to 1917, and then went to Yale University where he earned his B.A. in history (1921), M.A. in history (1922), and Ph.D. in history (1927). He joined the faculty of the University of Michigan in 1927 as an instructor, and then served as assistant professor, associate professor, and full professor. From 1942 to 1945 Ehrmann served in the U.S. Naval Reserve as a lieutenant and a lieutenant commander. After the war, he returned to the University of Michigan as professor of history. From 1953 to 1959, he served as chairman of the university's department of history. Ehrmann's last year of teaching was 1966/67; he retired in 1968.
Ehrmann's fields of interest were modern European history, European diplomatic history and international relations since 1871, recent Italian history, United States and world sea power, and the foreign policy of the United States. In addition to teaching in the department of history at the University of Michigan, he taught summer sessions at the University of Virginia, the University of Southern California, Stanford University, Centre Universitaire Mediterranean, Summer Seminar, Universite d'Aix Marseille, and the School of Advanced International Studies, Bologna Center, The Johns Hopkins University. Ehrmann was a member of the American Historical Association and directed the Whaddon Hall Project, the microfilming of the captured German Foreign Ministry Archives, in addition to co-directing the microfilming of the captured German Naval Archives. He published widely in the areas of concentration mentioned above, and also edited and reviewed many publications. From 1972 to 1975 he was historian at the Naval Ordnance Laboratory, and from 1975 to 1980 he was office historian for the office of the U.S. Secretary of Defense. Howard Ehrmann died in 1989.
The Howard M. Ehrmann Papers document the period 1927-1968, the length of Ehrmann's tenure at the University of Michigan. The collection includes correspondence relating in part to his chairmanship of the department of history at the University of Michigan, materials used in his classes such as tests and syllabi, materials documenting his activities as reviewer and editor, and materials documenting his writings, including a manuscript for a book The Second World War: A Political History of the Immediate Origins of the War, 1939-1941 which was never published. Of special interest are two folders of autographs of 20th century political figures such as Ralph Bunche, Herbert Hoover, and Alger Hiss, which were gathered by Professor Ehrmann when he was arranging a conference on the postwar world.
The collection has been arranged into the following series: Biographical/Personal; Courses; Correspondence - University of Michigan; General Correspondence; Research/Grants; Editing and Reviews; Writings; and Miscellaneous
Subjects:
Delta Kappa Epsilon. Omicron Chapter (University of Michigan); Ehrmann, Howard M. (Howard Meredith), 1898-1989; Europe--History--Study and teaching.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Historians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of History.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan. War Seminar.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Biographies / C.V. (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies (Box 1)
  - Autographs, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Courses
  - Naval History (Box 1)
  - Seminar Notes on World War I revisionism (Box 1)
  - 136/474, Modern Italy (Box 1)
  - 147, European Diplomatic History 1933-1947 (Box 1)
  - 153 (Box 1)
  - 198, Rise of American Sea Power (Box 1)
  - 241/645, Studies in European History since 1870 (Box 1)
  - 283, 284 (Box 1)
  - 318, Seminar in Recent European History (Box 1)
  - 454, European Diplomatic History 1904-1933 (Box 1)
  - 455, European Diplomatic History since 1933 (Box 1)
  - 592 (Box 1)
  - 720, Seminar in 20th century Europe (Box 1)
  - Ph.D. field exams (Box 1)
  - USC, summer term 1950 (Box 1)
  - Stanford, summer term 1953 (Box 1)
  - Stanford, lecture, summer 1953 (Box 1)
  - Johns Hopkins, Bologna 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re: Johns Hopkins, Bologna (Box 1)
- Correspondence-University of Michigan
  - Name files
    - Boak, A.E.R., dept. chair (Box 1)
    - Bowditch, John, dept. chair (Box 1)
    - Haber, William, Dean, LS&A (Box 1)
    - Hays, William L., Assoc. Dean, LS&A (Box 1)
    - Heyns, Roger W., Dean, LS&A (Box 1)
    - Lesch, James E., Ass't to Vice President for Academic Affairs (Box 1)
    - Lewis, Ralph B., Ass't to Dean, Rackham (Box 1)
    - Miller, Freeman, Assoc. Dean, Rackham (Box 1)
    - Vander Velde, Lewis, acting dept. chair (Box 1)
    - Willcox, William B., dept. chair (Box 1)
  - Topical Files
    - Brosio, Manlio (Box 1)
    - Department Chairmanship (Box 1)
    - Michigan Union (Box 1)
    - Richard Hudson professorship (Box 1)
    - Ritter, Gerhard lecturing (Box 1)
    - University Libraries (Box 1)
- General Correspondence
  - Name files
    - Bassani, G.L. (Box 1)
    - Bonnin, Georges, Ohio State University (Box 1)
    - Brower, Philip, National Archives (Box 1)
    - East, Sherrod, National Archives (Box 1)
    - Fisher, Harold H., Hoover Institute (Box 1)
    - Ford, Gerald, U.S. House of Representatives (Box 1)
    - Ford, Guy Stanton, AHA (Box 1)
    - Haines, C. Grove, Johns Hopkins, Bologna (Box 1)
    - Heffernan, John B., USN (Box 1)
    - Holborn, Hajo, Yale (Box 1)
    - Isaac, Jules, Paris (Box 1)
    - Kimball, Dan A., American University Tangiers (Box 1)
    - Kleiman, S.R., Washington Post (Box 1)
    - Lambert, Margaret (Box 1)
    - Langer, William L., Harvard (Box 1)
    - Lutz, Hermann (Box 1)
    - Mori, Renato (Box 1)
    - Namier, Sir Lewis B. (Box 1)
    - Noble, G. Bernard, Dept. of State, History. Division (Box 1)
    - Orlando letter (Box 1)
    - Schafer, Boyd C., AHA (Box 1)
    - Schmitt, Bernadotte, University of Chicago (Box 1)
    - Seymour, Charles, Yale (Box 1)
    - Sworakowski, Witold, Hoover Institute (Box 1)
    - Toscano, Mario (Box 1)
    - Tuchman, Barbara W. (Box 1)
  - Topical
    - American Historical Association (Box 1)
    - American Historical Association, Whaddon Hall project 1959 (Box 1)
    - Hoover Library, Stanford (Box 1)
    - Center for Cultural Interchange between East and West (Box 1)
    - Dante's 700th anniversary (Box 1)
    - Commissione americani per gli scambi culturali con l'Italia (Box 1)
    - Istituto per la storia del risorgimento Italiano (Box 1)
    - XLI congresso Istituto per la storia (Box 1)
    - XLIII congresso Istituto per la storia (Box 1)
    - Society For Italian Historical Studies (Box 1)
  - Chronological
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1936-1940 (Box 1)
    - 1941-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1960 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1967 (Box 1)
- Research/Grants
  - Correspondence
    - Fulbright 1953-1954 (Box 1)
    - Fulbright 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Leaves of Absence (Box 1)
    - British foreign office library (Box 1)
  - Project descriptions (Box 1)
  - Faculty research grants (Box 1)
- Editing and Reviews
  - Renouvin The Immediate Origins of the War, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Bloch Les Causes de la Guerre Mondiale, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Toscano Gli Accordi di San Giovanni di Moriana, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Sasse, "War das Deutsche Engreifen in die Bosniche Krise..." 1936 (Box 1)
  - Review of review of English translation of Bloch (Box 1)
  - Russell and Kniffen Culture Worlds, 1948 (Box 1)
  - History of Europe in the Twentieth Century, 1949 (Box 1)
  - I Documenti Diplomatici Italiani,1914-1918, 1958 (Box 1)
  - I Documenti Diplomatici Italiani,1922-1935, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Ashley volume of U of M History of the Modern World, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Medlicott From Metternich to Hitler, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Michel La Question de l'Adriatique, 1914-18 (Box 1)
  - Papers Relating to the Foreign Relations of the U.S., vols. v and vi, 1950 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - World War I
    - Articles on the July Crisis (Box 1)
    - Article-A Bibliographic Guide to the Study of International Relations 1870-1919 (Box 1)
    - Book Ms.-Italy in 1914, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Article-The Pact of London September 15, 1914 (Box 2)
    - Article-Recent American literature on the Intervention of the U.S. in the World War (Box 2)
    - Article-Underlying Causes of the War (Box 2)
  - World War II
    - Article-Britain's position in the Mediterranean (1942) (Box 2)
    - Article-Paris Peace Conference History 1939-1952, with Russell Fifield (Box 2)
    - Book ms.- The Second World War: A Political History of the Immediate Origins and First Years of the War, 1939-41, 1946, 5 folders (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - By topic
    - Centennial celebration of the unification of Italy 1961 (Box 2)
    - National Defense Committee, Ann Arbor 1940-1941 (Box 2)
    - Universite d'Aix Marseille, Cours d'Ete 1954 (Box 2)
    - Omicron Chapter, Delta Kappa Epsilon (Box 2)
  - By date
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1936-1940 (Box 2)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 2)